There are more kinds of insects in the world than all other kinds of animals put together.
世界上的昆虫种类繁多，数量加起比全部动物种类还要多。
But because they are so small,
但因为它们都很渺小，
we rarely see how extraordinary they are.
所以我们几乎看不到它们的存在有什么不平凡。
Occasionally, they assemble in astonishing numbers.
有时，它们以惊人的数量在一起。
A billion monarch butterflies hibernate in the forests of Mexico.
数不尽的帝王蝴蝶在墨西哥的森林里过冬。
Vast clouds of mayflies emerge all at once to mate.
大量的蜉蝣在同一时间出现接着交配。
Insects face endless challenges.
昆虫们正面临着无止境的挑战。
They can transform their bodies to meet every purpose -
它们能以自己的想法改变着自己的身体。
eyes grow onstalks. Bodies become chemical guns.
眼睛长在茎上。身体变成化学武器。
To discover how and why they do suchthings,
欲了解它们如何以及为什么做出这样的事，
you have to enter theirworld.
你就要进入它们的世界。
Patagonia, Chile, home to one of the most extraordinary of beetles.
在巴塔哥尼亚和智利是大量特别的甲虫的家。
There are many kinds of beetles in the world,
世界上有许多类型的甲虫，
but this one hassome of the biggest jaws of all.
然而这只甲虫拥有昆虫界里最大的角。
He is Darwin's beetle.
他叫“达尔文”甲虫。
He is on his way to the forest to look for a mate.
它在去往森林的途中寻找着伴侣。
Whether he gets one or not will depend on his strength...
为了寻找伴侣它将运用上它的力量
and on the size of his jaws.
和它的大角。
He starts his search.
它开始了它的征途。
A female is likely to be on a tree trunk.
雌性甲虫可能在树干上。
But trees, in this part of the world are very tall.
以它的体形而言这棵树非常的巨大。
His search could be a long one.
它的寻找将是十分漫长。
Unfortunately for him, she is 25 metres above him
不幸的是，雌性离它还有25米之距
near the top.
在树的最高处。
She has more normal-sized jaws.
雌性有着相对正常大小的角。
But thenshe only needs them for feeding.
雌性只需用它来摄取食物。
But he needs immense jaws forfighting...
然而雄性用它那双大角来搏斗。
..because there are other males aroundwith the same mission.
因为它们都有着相同的“使命”（繁殖交配）。
Sheer strength isnot enough in these battles.
在这场搏斗中光靠力量是不够的。
The technique is to reach over your opponent's head
这技巧就是碰到竞争对手的头部
and hook your jaws under his wing-covers.
用角钩住它的翼套。
That's why his jaws are so long
那就是为什么它们的角需要这么长
and have that odd shape.
而且有着奇怪的形状。
He's got the grip.
它能抓牢对方。
Now he as to lift.
现在他要把它举起。
And that needs strength.
但还需要些力气。
Another lift is needed.
其中一只需要被举起抛下。
And that's that.
事实就是这样。
Beetle armour is strong so he bounces.
它的外壳非常坚硬帮它吸收了弹力。
The winner climbs on.
胜利者继续往上爬。
There are more males ready to fight him up here.
途中许多雄性准备好向它挑战。
And here she is at last.
她（雌性）就在最后。
But she doesn't seem to be in the mood.
但她现在好像并没有做好准备（交配）的心情。
So now he has to use his great jaws as a restraining cage.
他只好用他那大角围成一个笼子强制她行动。
Success at last.
他终于成功了。
But the hurling habit dies hard.
然而死性难改，他把她抛了下去。
Insects' bodies have the capacity to take on an almostinfinite variety of shapes.
昆虫的外壳有着各种不同的外形和能力。
This is oneof the keys to their success.
那也是昆虫成功生存繁殖的原因之一。
This male moth doesn't go in search of females.
雄蛾并不去寻找雌蛾。
He inflates a pair of scented plumes
他膨胀那双有着特殊味道的双羽
that protrude from the end of his abdomen.
从他的腹部末端伸出来。
And they come to him!
雌性就会来找他了
All insects have the same basic design...
所有的昆虫都有着基本相同的部分...
six legs and an armour-covered body.
六只脚和一顶大盔甲
But the different parts can become exaggerated
但是不同的部分却变得很夸张
tosolve particular problems.
来满足各自的需要
This beetle has a giraffe's neck in order to fight.
这只甲虫那长颈鹿似的的脖子就用来搏斗。
A praying mantis is disguised as a flower
螳螂伪装成一花朵
and waits in ambush.
等待着埋伏着。
Another is almost invisible amongdead leaves.
这只螳螂运用了难以察觉的枯叶外型。
Insects' armour can carry colours that can camouflage or communicate.
昆虫的外壳能以丰富的颜色来伪装或交代信息。
But the armour can also be converted into wings
但也能由外壳转变成翅膀
and that makes insects a globalforce,
使昆虫遍布世界，
enabling them to invade almost every habitat on earth.
使它们能侵占地球的每一处并在那栖息
In Southern France,
在法国的南部，
one insect is starting on the most important day of its life.
一只昆虫开始着其生命中最重要的一天。
Dawn, and a newly hatched damselfly.
旁晚，一只刚长成（出壳）的豆娘（蜻蜓）。
She needs to mate and lay her eggs before sunset.
她要在日落前交配并且产卵。
Her adult life is so short, she may not get another chance.
她成虫的时间非常短，她没有第二次机会了。
Her success will depend on these fragile wings.
她的成功将依靠那脆弱的翅膀。
She faces many perils.
她面临许多危险。
Few insects can escape from a spider's web.
很少昆虫能逃脱蜘蛛的网。
But her wings are more powerful thanthey look.
她的翅膀比看起来有劲。
She wants to mate with the strongest male.
她想和强壮的雄性配对。
However, the stream, where she might find him, is a battle-ground.
然而，能寻找到雄性的小溪却是一个战场。
She watches while dark-winged males compete for the best territories,
她注视着，黑色翅膀的雄性取得最佳地盘的竞争。
flashing their wings at each other in threat,
挥动翅膀相互威胁着，
or trying to force their opponents into the water.
或者用武力将他们的竞争对手压到水面。
Fighting finished, the female uses her wings to signal her presence to the winner.
竞争结束后，雌性用她的翅膀做暗号对胜利者说明她的到来。
She won't be rushed.
她不匆不忙。
But if he doesn't grip her with his tail, a rival might steal her.
如果雄性不抓住雌性的尾部，对手可能会抢走雌性。
As they mate, their linked bodies form the shape of a heart.
当它们配对成功，它们交配时的外型像个心型。
But now she has the problem of laying her fertilised eggs and that brings new hazards.
但是另一个问题来了，她产卵时会遇到很多风险。
Like any athlete, she must warm her muscles for optimum performance
像一些运动员那样，她会先热身
and does so by using her wings as solar-heating panels.
她们利用太阳加热翅膀。
She must fly dangerously low if she's to find the right place for her eggs.
想找到合适的产卵地儿就必须危险的低飞。
Only the quickest damselflies escape.
只有最敏捷的豆娘才能逃脱
Safely past the frogs,
安全的逃离了青蛙，
this femalehas reached a suitable planton which to lay her eggs.
这些雌性找到一处合适的地方产卵。
But she has to place them underwater if they are to survive.
如果她们刚都幸存下来就要到水下来。
For the first time, her wings seem to be a hindrance.
她的翅膀看上去是一个妨碍。
But in fact, they help her yet again,
但事实上，她的翅膀是有一次帮了她，
by trapping a silvery layer of air which enables her to breathe.
翅膀上银色的一层其实是空气，这样她就能呼吸了。
She cuts into a plant stem and deposits her eggs inside.
她尾部刺入植物的茎部在里面产下了她的卵。
Now herwings are going to be truly tested.
现在，她的翅膀将是面临真正的考验。
If she can't break through the water surface, she will drown.
如果她不能突破水面她将会溺死。
Her day has been a complete success.
她圆满的成功了 。
Damselflies seldom venture beyond their home stream.
豆娘在小溪里罕见的冒险。
But some insects fly huge distances.
但是一些昆虫要飞很长的距离。
September on the shores of Lake Erie in Southern Canada.
九月在加拿大南部的伊利湖湖畔
A monarch butterfly is fuelling up on nectar.
一只帝王蝴蝶正采集着花蜜。
A chill gust of Northerly air.
一阵北方空气的寒冷阵风
It's time to leave.
是它该离开的时候。
The coming winter will be so cold it would kill her.
即将到来的冬天会是如此寒冷会将她冻死。
She has never flown more than a few hundred metres in her life.
在她的生命里她从来没有飞超过几百米。
But now she is heading out over Lake Erie,
但现在她飞离伊利湖，
which is a hundred miles across.
这是一百英里的路程。
This is just the first leg of one of the greatest animal migrations.
这仅仅是最伟大的动物迁徙的第一站。
She will continue South, using thesun as a compass,
她将继续南行，利用太阳作为罗盘，
to cross America, a journey of 2,000 miles.
穿越美国，将是两千英里的旅程。
Her destination is Mexico and one small and special group of trees.
她的目的地是墨西哥的一处小而且特别的树林。
No-one knows how she finds them, in these great mountain forests.
没有人知道它们是如何从这片大山林里找到这处地方的。
She joins other monarch butterflies that have travelled here from all over North America.
她加入其他帝王蝴蝶，它们都来至各北美地区。
Countless butterflies crowd these particular trees,
无数的蝴蝶挤满了这片特别的树林。
hanging from every branch.
挂满了每棵枝条。
They come here because, although winter brings a chill to the air,
它们来到这里是因为冬天带来了寒冷的空气，
there will not be a lethal freeze as there will in Canada.
在加拿大它们不会寒冷致死。
The conditions are perfect for hibernation.
这里的条件有利于过冬。
Hibernating butterflies are vulnerable to predators.
冬眠中的帝王蝴蝶十分易受到其他动物的攻击。
But monarchs are poisonous.
但是帝王蝴蝶是有剧毒的。
However, a few birds have learned to rip out the toxic parts and eat the rest.
然而，一些小鸟学会了祛除帝王蝴蝶其有毒的部分吃下没毒部分。
They kill hundreds of thousands of butterflies and dislodge many more.
它们杀死成千上万的蝴蝶，还有许多是被迫赶下了树。
Those that fall must get back into the trees before nightfall brings another killer.
那些掉下了树的蝴蝶必须回到树上，因为夜里带里另一个“杀手”。
They vibrate their wings to warm their flight muscles.
他们颤动翅膀想要回暖翅膀。
But it's a race against time.
但这是与时间赛跑。
Night brings a lethal ground frost.
夜里待在地上会被冻伤的。
Those that do survive, sleep safely huddled together in the trees, for four months.
四个月过去了，那些挤在树上冬眠的蝴蝶都能存活下来。
The warmth of spring wakes them from their hibernation.
温暖的春天把它们从冬眠的状态唤醒过来。
The majority of the butterflies that flew here from Canada have survived.
大多数幸存的蝴蝶都是从加拿大飞往过来的。
They take their first drink since their arrival last autumn.
他们吸食着至去年秋天到现在的第一口饮料。
With increasing warmth, more and more butterflies awake.
当越来越温暖的时候，更多的蝴蝶也将苏醒过来。
Soon they will all disperse northwards
不久它们将分散北移
and tranquillity will return to this forest
这片森林也将返回安宁
untilthe great grandchildren of these butterflies return to escape the freezing Northern winter.
直到这些蝴蝶的子孙为了逃避寒冷又再次回来这里。
Some insects, however, have made a speciality of living in the most adverse conditions.
然而，有些昆虫，有能力生活在非常不利的环境下。
Mono Lake is known as California's dead sea.
莫诺湖被称为美国加洲的死海。
It's twice as salty as the ocean and lethal to almost all life.
比海水还要咸两倍的湖水对于任何生物来说都是致命的。
Alkali flies are one of the few creatures able to tolerate these conditions
碱苍蝇是少数能忍受这种环境的动物之一
and since they have virtually no competitors,
实际上它们几乎没有竞争对手，
they swarm in their millions.
他们数以百万的聚集在这里。
Flies are one of the most successful of all insects.
苍蝇是所有最成功的昆虫之一
There are 85,000 different kinds
它们有85,000不同种类
and among them, a perfect fly for almost every habitat, even this one.
每种苍蝇都能很好的适应每处环境，甚至在这里
The alkali fly has special abilities that enable it to live on this lake.
碱苍蝇具有特殊能力，使它们能够生活在这个湖
It can walk underwater to eat algae.
它们能到水下吃藻类。
Fine hairs trap air bubbles that prevent it from drowning.
纤细的茸毛收集气泡防止它们被溺死。
But most critically, the flyhas a physiology
但最关键的是苍蝇的生理机能
that can neutralise the lethal levels of salt.
能中和盐的致命成分
So the alkali fly's dominance of Mono Lake goes unchallenged
所以碱苍蝇支配了莫诺湖并未受到挑战
except for a few weeks of the year.
除了一年里的几周。
100,000Wilson's phalarope are migrating to South America.
100,000的威尔逊 矶鹞迁移到了南美洲。
Mono Lake is their only stop-over.
莫诺湖是他们唯一休息站。
These alkali flies, for them, are an invaluable and irresistible feast.
这些碱苍蝇，对它们来说，却是宝贵和不可抗拒的盛宴。
A fly has no defence, except tofly and become lost in a vast swarm.
苍蝇没有防备的方法，除了飞和大量的减少。
It needs considerable skill to pluck an individual fly from the air.
它需要相当的技巧来吃到飞行中的苍蝇。
There are gulls are here, too.
当然这里还有许多海鸥。
Though their fly-catching techniques are not so refined.
虽然它们抓苍蝇的技巧并没有那么好。
In four weeks, the phalaropes double their weight.
在这四个星期里，矶鹞体重增加了一倍。
Then they set off again, heading south.
它们再度向南出发。
Leaving the gulls behind.
海鸥也在它们后出发。
The size of the fly population has scarcely been affected.
苍蝇种群数量几乎没有受到影响。
For them, sheer abundance is defence enough.
对它们来说，数量就是一种防御。
BUZZING
嗡嗡响
But for some insects, defence is a much more complicated affair.
但对于某些昆虫，防御是一项十分复杂的事情。
An oogpister beetle in South Africa.
在南非的A甲虫。（oogpister就用A来做代称吧）
He hunts ants.
它捕食蚂蚁。
Eating ants may give him more than just nourishment.
吃蚂蚁，可给予它的不只是填饱肚子。
He may get something else from them that helps him fight his enemies.
它可能会找些其他帮助打退它的敌人。
The ants launch a counter-attack and nip his ankles.
蚂蚁发动反击，并咬他的脚踝。
But he simply kicks them out of the way.
但他只是用踢飞的方式（哈哈）
The valiantants drive him off...
勇敢的蚂蚁击退了它...
straight into real danger.
直接进入真正的危险。
A mongoose.
一只猫鼬。
It's inquisitive.
它是好奇的动物。
But it's also wary of the oogpister.
但它也提防着A。
A black and white pattern is a warning signal.
黑和白的图案是种警告信号。
The beetle takes aim...
甲虫它瞄准着...
And fires formic acid straight at the mongoose's eyes and mouth.
火蚁的蚁酸都被喷到了猫鼬的眼睛和嘴巴上了。
The beetle probably collected this acid from the ants.
A可能是从蚂蚁那收集了酸液。
It certainly makes the beetle itself very distasteful and that, in turn, makes it worth mimicking.
这无疑也是甲虫非常讨厌的酸液，但这次，它也好好利用了酸液模仿了蚂蚁的角式。
This defenceless little lizard carries the beetles' warning pattern.
这手无寸铁的小蜥蜴，背上也有着甲虫那样的警告色。
It also imitates the way the beetle runs.
也模仿着甲虫的走路样子。
Not particularly well, it's true, but well enough to
不是特别好，这是真的，但足够了。
fool predators into thinking it just might be an acid-firing beetle.
以为愚弄食肉动物它只是可能是酸烧虫。
All kinds of insects have developed chemical weapons.
各种昆虫都有着化学武器的发展。
A pair of devil-rider stick insects.
一只条纹竹节虫。
They fire bitter-tasting oils, terpenes.
它们喷射出苦味的油，□烯
European wood ants under attack from a hungry crow.
受到饥饿的乌鸦攻击的欧洲木蚂蚁
They fire the sort of acid that gives nettles their sting,
蚂蚁喷射出的酸性液体使乌鸦感到刺痛
so this is like one of us falling into a nettle patch.
就像让人陷入棘手的麻烦。
But the master of chemical warfare is the bombardier beetle.
但真正的化学战的大师乃是投弹甲虫。
It can create a chemical reaction within it's body so violent
它可以创建剧烈的体内化学反应室
that boiling caustic liquid explodes out of its abdomen.
炽热的腐蚀性液体从它的腹部处迅速喷出。
By pulsing the jet 500 times a second,
通过脉冲射500次1秒
it keeps its rear end just cool enough to prevent it being cooked.
它们尾部有冷却系统以防止它被煮熟
In the woodlands of Minnesota,
在明尼苏达州的林地，
there is an insect that has another chemical weapon.
这里一种昆虫，还有另一种化学武器。
But this one fights as an army and can stand up to almost any predator.
他们战斗的时候就像一名军人，勇敢的对抗全部食肉动物。
Bees collect nectar all day and transform it, within their stomachs,
蜂蜜辛勤的收集花蜜和转换它，储存在它们胃里，
into one of nature's richest foods, honey.
自然界营养丰富的食物，蜂蜜。
Hundreds of them are bringing their precious loads back to their colony in this hollow log.
数以百计的它们每日工作就是把宝贵的“负担”带回了它们的巢穴。
The honey in their combs provides food for their young
它们用蜂蜜喂养着后代
and for the whole colony if the weatherturns cold or there's a drought.
还存储起来以应付天气的转冷或着干旱。
But so much food attracts thieves.
但是如此多的食品也吸引了小偷。
A black bear cub has a sweet tooth.
幼小的黑熊喜欢甜食。
But he's never come across bees before
但它从来没有遇到以前蜜蜂
and he doesn't know that they will defend their honey to the death.
它并不知道蜜蜂将捍卫他们的蜂蜜直到战死
Stinging is the ultimate self-sacrifice for a bee,
蛰刺最终会导致蜜蜂自己的死亡，
because itcan't pull out its barbed sting.
因为它们不能拔出倒刺。
So its body is torn apart.
因此，它的身体也将被撕裂。
The bees' attack was far too much for the cub.
蜜蜂猛烈的攻击幼熊。
But a greater challenge is coming.
但更大的挑战即将到来。
The cub's mother!
幼熊的妈妈
ANGRY BUZZING
愤怒的嗡嗡声
The bees fight so hard that she only has time to steal a single comb.
蜜蜂抵抗到底，熊妈妈只有一次偷一点
While the family enjoy their honey at a safe distance,
熊家庭在远离蜂巢的安全距离享用着蜂蜜
the beesappear to have been defeated.
蜜蜂似乎被打败了
Their home has been destroyed
它们的家已被毁坏
and their young will inevitably die out in the open.
而它们的后代也不可避免的因为曝露在外而死去
Yet the colony is not doomed because the workers are now rescuing at least some of what really matters...
然而群体不会就这样灭亡，工人们正营救着最后真正的关键
..their honey.
它们的蜂蜜
Each survivor is able to eat its own weight in honey, storing it in its stomach.
存活下来的蜜蜂们吃下和它体重相当的蜂蜜存储在它们胃里
They will have to abandon their dying young,
它们会丢弃它们的后代
but they will take much of their precious honey with them
但它们会保留那宝贵的蜂蜜
to sustain themselves while they build a new colony.
这将支撑着它们建立新的巢穴
Working together in such an organised society is the insects' great innovation.
有组织的一起工作就像昆虫里的社会化改革
So how did it begin?
那么，怎样开始
It may have started in a place like this -
它可能已经在这样一个地方开始
the nest of the Japanese red bug.
日本红虫的巢穴里
Parent insects don't usually care for their offspring but this bug is different.
成年昆虫通常不会照顾后代，但是这种甲虫则不是
The young feed on fallen fruit from just one kind of rare tree.
幼虫以一种珍惜的树的果实为食
They could never find it by themselves. So theirmother collects it for them.
幼虫们无法靠自己来采集，一次它们的母亲为它们收集它。
She probes every fruit she finds
她先品尝每个她找到的果子
to test its ripeness
以试它的成熟度
and rejects one after another.
并丢弃了一个又一个
This can take hours.
这需要耗费几个小时
At last, a perfect fruit.
最后找到一个完美的水果
A thief!
一小偷
It's easier to steal than find food for yourself.
窃取易于自己去麻烦寻找食物
For both bugs, the outcome of this dispute will be life-changing.
两个发疯似的在挣抢，但是也正将演示一幕大变化
As the mother struggles to keep herprize,
甲虫妈妈努力的保护它的果子
her young, back in the nest, are growing restless.
她的幼虫在巢穴里急躁不安
The thief has won.
小偷得到最终胜利
The mother doesn't know that her hungry young are leaving their nest in search of a better provider.
甲虫妈妈不知道它那饥饿的幼虫们离开了巢穴去寻找更好的养育者
She returns
甲虫妈妈回来了
to find that her nest is empty.
发现它的巢穴此时已经空了
Her young find the nest of the thief, who is herself a mother.
她的幼虫们找食却来到了刚才那小偷的巢穴
She returns to find that she has twice as many mouths to feed.
她回来的时候发现突然多了许多幼虫
The loser has failed at her only chance of parenthood.
失败者输的是当父母的立场
For the thief, life has suddenly got much harder.
对于小偷而言，生活变得更难了
A fruitwon't now last as long as it did.
食物无法永远吃不完
The youngclamber over her, demanding more.
幼虫爬到它身上，要求得到更多的食物
She returns with another fruit but her enlarged and
她领着果子回来了但她不得不加力度寻找食物
insatiable brood want still more.
贪得无厌的幼虫需要更加
So she has towork non-stop, day after day.
所以她不得不没天没夜的工作找食物
At last, the young become big enough to fend for themselves.
终于，幼虫长大到有能力自己去寻找食物
But their success has come at a cost.
但她们的成功是有代价的
The mother has worked herself to death.
甲虫妈妈辛勤的工作致死
And now her body hasbecome their last meal before they leave home.
现在她的身体成为了她幼虫们最后一顿食物接着离开巢穴
Looking after the young in such a way
照顾自己的幼虫以这种方式
is thought to be the first step towards living in a community.
被认为是踏入社会生活的第一步
But some insects benefit from doing the opposite of collaborating.
但是，一些做出相反的合作行为的昆虫却受益
They kill one another.
他们互相残杀
Dawson's bee is one of the largest in the world.
道森蜜蜂是全球蜜蜂的体形里最大的
It nests in the baked soil of the Australian outback.
它们在澳洲内陆被太阳晒干的土壤中筑巢
Flowers are rare in thisdesert, so colonies of these bees are few and far between.
花在的沙漠这乃罕见，所以这里蜜蜂巢穴是寥寥可数
The bees excavate tunnels fortheir young.
道森蜜蜂挖掘隧道来养育的幼虫
The community is so harmonious that it's hard to believe that this place
让人很难相信，巢穴间是如此和谐
is also the setting for mass murder.
但也是大屠杀的环境
Tempers do flare when a bee gets confused and goes down another's burrow.
如果一只蜜蜂糊涂的进入到别人的巢穴，主人脾气就不好了
But these are minor disagreements.
不过这些都是次要的分歧
The colony is peaceful at the moment becauseevery bee here is a female.
巢穴的是和平的时刻，因为每一个在这里蜜蜂都是雌性
It's the males that are the killers and they are all dead.
雄性则是杀手把它们全部都杀光了
Their story began two monthsearlier,
它们的故事始于两个月前
before theappearance of the females.
在雌性出现之前
Male Dawson's bees.
雄性道森蜜蜂
The females are only just emerging, burrowing their way, one by one,
雌性才刚刚出现，逐个以挖洞的方式出现
out of the tunnels where they hatched and grew up
她们走出隧道和孵化成长
and their scent enflames the males.
她们的气味吸引着雄性
They arehuge and built for fighting.
他们体形巨大，挖掘地洞迎合搏斗
And each one wants to be in the best position to mate with a female.
而每一只雄性都想要占有有利的位置配对雌性
A female emerges and immediately there's a brawl
一雌性出现马上引起打斗
as every male tries to reach her.
每只雄性都想接着雌性
It's very rare for animals to kill their own kind in combat,
在打斗中杀死对方这很少在动物界发生
but stinging and biting rivals to death
把竞争对手刺死
is usually the only way these male bees get a female.
通常是唯一途径获得这些雄蜂
A winner manages to claim a female and the pair race for cover.
胜利者能控制雌性，两者包在一起
Meanwhile, the female's lingering scent drives one unsuccessful male
同时，雌性挥之不去的气味继续吸引着失败的雄性们
into a deadly frenzy.
变成了疯狂的杀戮
Another female, caught in the middle of another brawl, becomes an accidental casualty.
另一个雌性，在另一斗殴事件中被捕，成为一个意外伤亡
By the time the last female has emerged, every male is dead.
到最后的女性出现时，全部雄蜂都死亡了
The battles have ensured that the strongest males will have mated with the most females.
战役确保了强大的雄性会与最多雌性交配
Two months later and it's an all female world
两个月过后变成了雌性的天下
with thenext generation already developing underground.
下一代已经在地下发育着
Insects have evolved sophisticated societies that, in complexity,
昆虫已经进化发展为成熟的社会而且复杂
are the closest thing in nature to our own cities.
实际上已经接近我们的城市生活。
The insects that built this structure in Argentina
在阿根廷昆虫以这种结构建立着
dominate the surrounding grasslands thanks to skills that seem almost more human than insect.
支配着周围草原的行为看上去更像是人类多于昆虫。
It's a metropolis,
这是一个大都市，
a home to millions of ants.
一个数以百万计的蚂蚁家族。
The colony needs a huge supply of food.
蚂蚁家族需要大量食物。
It's surrounded by grass,
它的周围环绕着草，
but the ants themselves can't digest a blade of it.
但蚂蚁本身无法消化叶片。
Nonetheless, they collect it.
虽然如此，它们收集叶片。
Although they're all the same species, they exist in different shapes and sizes.
虽然它们是同一种类，但是它们有不同的外形和大小。
The heads of these big-jawed individuals are not full of brain...
个别拥有大颚的蚂蚁头脑并不发达
but brawn.
但是肌肉发达。
They give the species its name.
它们有特别的名字
They are grass cutters.
它们叫切叶蚁
They work all day, every day.
每一天他们都辛勤工作
The smaller ants, down on the ground, are porters with the job
个头较小的蚂蚁，趴在地上，它们的工作是搬运工
of carrying the grass segments back to the colony.
搬运草片回到巢穴
They have great strength. Their main problem is balance.
它们力气很大，主要的问题就是如何取得平衡
Columns of them carry the grass back to the nest along highways
它们扛着叶片走着运输大道赶回巢穴
as straight as Roman roads.
仿佛是罗马的笔直道路
Different members of the colony specialise in particular tasks inmuch the same way as people do.
不同的成员负责不同专业的任务，跟人类一样分工明确
But, as in human society, there can be problems.
但是，要在人类社会，就可能会有冲突
A hitch-hiker makes one ant's job much harder.
对扛的蚂蚁而言有搭顺风车的同伴在会十分费力
And this isn't even grass.
它们不光搬运草片
A single colony harvests half a tonneof grass a year,
一个蚂蚁家族一年需要半吨草
more thanany other animal on these plains.
比在这个平原上任何一种动物需要的还多
But since they themselves can't eat it, why do they do so?
但是它们本身并不吃草片，那它们收集草片作何用呢？
The answer lies underground.
答案在于地下
They haveone of most extraordinary survivalstrategies in the insect world.
它们拥有昆虫世界最不寻常的生存战略
The ants have dug a network oftunnels
蚂蚁挖一个隧道网
that extend downwards for over seven metres.
一直向下延长可达7米多
At the heart of the colony lies the key to their survival. A fungus.
在殖民地的核心是其生存的关键。真菌
But this isn't sloppy house-keeping.
但是这并不是一件马虎的内务工作
This is a fungus that is found nowhere else on earth.
这些真菌在别处都找不到
And the ants cultivate it assiduously.
这是蚂蚁们辛勤耕种
The big-jawed ants chop up the grass covering it with an
大颚蚂蚁咬碎草片
antibiotic saliva that kills every kind of fungus except this one.
唾液里含有抗生素来清洁草片
The ants are farmers.
蚂蚁是农民
They feed the grass to the fungus
这些草来培育的真菌
and the fungus thrives.
真菌的蓬勃发展
The ants cultivate dozens of these fungus gardens throughout the colony.
蚂蚁们在巢穴的没处都培育了真菌
This is what they eat.
这才是他们的食物
The system is so efficient that a single colony can have five million members.
蚂蚁家族是非常有效率的一个大家庭，可以有500万名成员
But the fungus is also dangerous.
真菌也是个危险
As it grows it releases carbon dioxide that could asphyxiate the entire colony.
真菌生长时排放出的二氧化碳会使整个巢穴窒息
The ants' way of dealing with this danger is ingenious.
蚂蚁巧妙的应付这个危机
They construct their nest so that it has an automatic air-conditioning system.
它们建造的巢穴，使之具有自动循环空气的系统。
The outer surface is so shaped thatthe slightest breeze
外表面是如此形状能接收微风
sucks out staleair through these central vents.
通过这些中央通风口呼出混浊空气通风之用
At the same time, fresh air is drawn down through the outer vents,
同时，通风口提取外的通风口，
right into the heart of the nest.
右入巢的中心
Our own societies have existed for thousands of years
我们自己的社会已经存在了几千年
but insectsocieties have lasted for millions.
但昆虫社会已持续了百万年
There may be ten million different kinds of insects
可能有一千万不同种类的昆虫
and there are 200 million individuals for every one of us.
200万种对应我们一个人类
The insects' flexible armour and their adaptability
昆虫的灵活外壳和他们的适应能力
has made them the most abundant andthe most diverse animal group in our planet's history.
昆虫以数量最多，物种也最多样化的在我们的地球继续生活着
The Sierra Madre Mountains in Mexico
位于墨西哥的马德雷山脉
are home to one of the greatest natural wonders.
是世界上最美丽的一个物种的家园
A billion bright orange butterflies offered the Life team a wonderful filming challenge.
十亿只帝王蝴蝶 (学名:大桦斑蝶) 给了Life摄制组一次奇妙而用充满挑战的拍摄经验
The colonies are only found above 3,000 metres
这片帝王蝶的聚居地只有在海拔3000米的地方才能找到
and the team trek there slowly in the thin air.
摄制组在稀薄的空气中长途跋涉进行拍摄
The monarch phenomenon was only discovered here around 30 years ago and one man has been studying
帝王蝶迁徙的壮观场面在这里只在30年前被发现过一次 而有个人一直研究着它们
them every year since, Professor Lincoln Brower.
他是林肯．布鲁维尔教授
His knowledge will be essential if the team are to achieve their goal
如果摄制组能够成功通让摄影机在蝴蝶群当中"飞"过 拍摄它们的迁徙
of flying a camera among the butterflies.
那对于教授的研究绝对是不可多得宝贵资料
It's amazing that the butterflies only come to this area
让人很惊讶的是帝王蝶只会来这个地区
that's about 30 by 60 miles in extent.
这个地区的面积有30乘60英里那么大
There are other areas that have high forests,
在另一些地区有很多高树
in different parts of Mexico, to the west of here, to the south of here,
在墨西哥的不同地区, 从这里到西方, 再到南方
but as far as we know, this is the only place that monarchs are able to spend the winter.
不过据我们所知 这里是帝王蝶唯一能够度过冬天的地方
The butterflies are in such numbers that filming them the traditional way,
用传统的方法拍摄如此大数量的蝴蝶
from a camera on a tripod, is reasonably straightforward.
把摄影机架在三脚架上拍摄显然是件容易的事情
But to get a butterfly's viewpoint by flying a camera amongst
不过如果要摄影机跟随一只蝴蝶的视角
the swarms is going to be altogether more difficult.
身处在蝶群中拍摄则是非常困难的
First, the team need a spot where butterflies gather in huge numbers.
首先, 摄制组要找到一个地方有数量庞大的蝴蝶聚集
Luckily, Lincoln knows a place where thousands come down to drink every day.
很幸运的是 林肯教授知道有一处地方每天都有成千上万的蝴蝶去饮水
The crew spend the next three days preparing the equipment -
摄制组马上准备设备, 他们将会在那个地方呆上三天
a remote-controlled camera, a lot of cable, two bicycle wheels, a bag of rocks and some muscle-power.
一部遥控摄影机, 一堆缆索, 两个自行车轮子, 一大包石头, 还要摄制组成员的人力
Now all they need to do is wait until the butterfly numbers reach truly impressive proportions.
现在他们需要做的是等待 直到蝴蝶的数量真正达到让人惊叹不已的地步
By mid-day, the butterflies are swarming
在正午时分, 蝴蝶成群出动
and it's time for the camera to glide with them through the air.
现在是是时候让摄影机跟随蝴蝶在空中滑翔
Three and away.
倒数三声之后开始
Superb. OK, let's just stop that.
太棒了, 好了, 可以停下来了
Absolutely stunning.
绝对是让人惊叹不已
We've got great numbers coming in. Let's keep going
我们现在已经等到非常大量的蝴蝶出现, 继续拍摄吧
and then we'll do a turn round shot.
接着我们将会回头给它们一个镜头
A series of unique shots flying withthe butterflies.
这是一系列跟随着蝴蝶群拍摄的独一无二的镜头
But that was the easy part.
不过这些都是没什么难度的了
Now it's time to get the camera 50 metres up into the tree tops.
现在是时候把摄影机架到离地50米高树顶上面
Filming the roosting butterflies is not going to be simple, the clusters are unstable.
要拍摄栖息中的蝴蝶群并非易事 因为这些蝶群的聚集并不稳定
And they can suddenly disperse without warning,
它们会在毫无征兆的情况下突然退散
what Lincoln calls an explosion!
林肯教授把这种大规模的蝶群退散称作"大爆炸"!
Here'sanother explosion. Wow, look at that!
这是另一次的"大爆炸", 哇, 快看看
And they're going right over our head.
它们正在我们的头顶飞过
Spectacular, no doubt, but a real problem for the climbing team, Jim Spickler and Tim Fogg.
毫无疑问这实在太壮观了 不过对于摄影师Jim Spickler和Tim Fogg来说 爬上高树这的是个大问题
Would it be better for us to start now?
现在有没有一个更好的方法让我们开始拍摄?
we're gonna be very careful not to disturb them,
我们会很小心翼翼地在不打扰它们的情况下拍摄
or limit our disturbance, but if we do disturb them right now
或者说最大限度减少我们的打扰 不过貌似我们现在已经打扰它们了
it seems that they're warm enough that they could relocate to a cluster right adjacent to them,
它们看起来已经度过寒冬 会重新回到邻近的蝶群
do you think that's true?
你觉得那是真的吗?
Well, if you disturb them they tend to fly away from the tree, 50 feet or so,
如果你打扰了它们, 它们就会朝着某个方向飞离高树 飞到50英尺或者更加高
so you'll lose those clusters I think if you disturb them.
所以如果你打扰了它们, 你就会跟丢整个蝶群
Do you think they'll cluster again though, tomorrow night?Idoubt it.
你觉得它们会再度聚集到一块吗? 明天晚上? 我对此表示怀疑
< I think they'll just move down.
我觉得它们会往下走
That's really hard stuff, you know because I can't seehow we can get up the trees
这的确是件难事, 因为我们不知道怎么爬到这些树上去
and do what we have to up there,
不管怎样我们还是要想方设法爬到树上
close to any clusters without them flying.
尽可能接近任何一个蝶群而不惊动它们
I just don't know how I'm gonna be able to get an arrow into the tree.
我不知道如何能够把一支箭固定在树上
I think if you picked your tree, you could put the arrow in it now.
我想如果你已经选定好了一棵树 你现在就可以把箭固定在树上
The prospect of rigging cables high in the canopy, without disturbing
悄悄地把缆索悬挂在半空中
the butterflies is a daunting one. They may only get one chance.
这些蝴蝶都是极度容易受惊 所以摄制组也许只有一次机会
One false move and it'll all be gone.
做错一个步骤就会让整个拍摄告吹
I had the impression that they might come back but
我有一种感觉它们也许会再回来的
Lincoln says they just won't, they'll just move on to another tree.
但是林肯教授说他们不会回来, 它们只会飞到另一棵树上
So we put all the rigging in, disturb them and then...
所以如果我们在悬挂缆索时打扰到它们...
that's it!
那就完了!
Choosing which trees to rig is a critical decision.
挑选哪些树去悬挂缆索是个至关重要的决定
Can you get right to tree number six do you think, or is that too far?
你看看能不能拉到"六号"树, 或是那太远了?
They begin by firing a line over a suitably high branch.
他们开始用十字弓对着合适高度的树枝发射绳索
That'll work.
成功了
Nobody, not even Lincoln, knows how the butterflies will react.
没有人, 即使是林肯教授, 也不知道那些蝴蝶将会有什么反应
Yeah that's gonna work perfect, I think.
太好了, 我觉得绝对没问题
OK, great.
哦, 太棒了
I've got to do a changeover here so just give me a moment.
看来我得要完全改变一下计划, 给我一点时间
There's an explosion.
那里有一次"大爆炸"
Thankfully, it's not in the trees that Jim and Tim are rigging with such care.
但幸运的是, 那并非Jim和Tim小心悬挂缆索的那棵树
Can you just push it towards me a bit?
你能够把我往前推一点吗?
Ouch.You OK?
哎哟, 你没事吧?
Yep.OK, get your fingers out.
没事, 没事, 把你的手指放开
OK, that's good.
好的, 那好了
It takes another three days to get theaerial rig set up, followed by many hours of fine tuning.
摄制组需要多用三天时间去架设悬空的缆索 接着还要花很多时间去调试
Just pan it so we don't see it in the monitor, please.
请把它放平, 这才能让我们在屏幕上看不到它
Everything is finally set and the butterflies are still there.
最终万事俱备, 蝴蝶依然在那里
One, two, three.
一, 二, 三
Take one.
镜头一
Too slow.
太慢了
There was no load at the beginning
在开始时候就没有弄好
and thensuddenly it just completely stopped.
之后突然间摄影机完全停住了
Take six.
镜头六
Keep going. Start to slow, slow and keep going, keep going, keep going.
继续. 开始时慢些, 慢些, 之后继续, 继续, 继续
OK, Mike, hold it.
好的, Mike, 停住
Not far enough.
还是不行
We've not got enough weight, Jim.
Jim, 我们的重量不足够
Take nine.
镜头九
Go on, Mike.
继续, Mike
Go on, Mike. Get in close, Mike, now start slowing.
继续上, Mike. 再靠近一点, 现在开始慢一些
OK.
好的
It's still not right and now time is running out.
还是未能成功, 而时间也所剩无几了
I think the light's going.
我想是光线问题
Shall we do one last take?
我们还要再拍最后一次吗?
All right. Because these ones here, we're losing the light on them.
好的. 因为这里有一群, 我们好像错过了它们
Try and get a shot that's going past here if it's smooth.
如果顺利的话, 尝试在经过这里的时候拍一个镜头
One, two, three, and we're away.
一, 二, 三, 我们开始
Take 17.
镜头十七
And it's looking good.
一切看起来都很顺利
OK, start slowing, Mike. OK, keep it going, keep it going.
好的, Mike, 开始慢些, 好的, 继续, 继续这样
Success at last.
最终大功告成
With the technique now working, the crew rig more and more shots
现在这手法已证实行得通,摄制组架设更多缆索和拍了更多
to give an aerial perspective on the monarch phenomenon.
由远而近的帝王蝶群的镜头
His work advising the crew over, Lincoln continues the observations
林肯教授完成了给摄制组当顾问的工作后,他继续着观察研究
he's been making for over a quarter of a century.
他做这项工作已超过25年
Although the butterflies are still here in immense numbers,
虽然蝴蝶的数目仍然是非常巨大
he's worried there is a threat to their survival.
他担心蝴蝶的生存环境正受到很大威胁
The big, huge influx, maybe sometimes as many as two billion butterflies,
蝴蝶大量涌入的数目是惊人的, 大约20亿只
flying down into this tiny area of 30 by 60 miles,
它们都飞到这个30乘60英里的弹丸之地
is thoroughly endangered by illegal logging.
非法的砍伐让这些蝴蝶很快就要面临绝种
If the forest is not protected the phenomenon will be lost.
如果森林得不到保护, 如此壮观的景象就会消失
It'd be a disaster.
那会是灾难
I mean, it would be like taking the Mona Lisa out of the Parisian museum and,
我的意思是,这就是好比把"蒙娜丽莎"的真迹从巴黎的博物馆拿走
and burning it up.
然后付之一炬